A Finding Aid to the Allen Saalburg Papers, 1924-circa 2003, bulk 1940-1987, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Allen Saalburg papers
1924-circa 2003
bulk 1940-1987
Archives of American Art
Saalburg, Allen Russell, 1899-1987
AAA.saalalle
Archival Resource Key
0.8 Linear feet
The papers of painter, illustrator, and screenprinter Allen Saalburg, 1924-circa 2003, bulk 1940-1987, measure 0.8 linear feet. Included are professional correspondence, printed material, a scrapbook and photographs. Most photographs are of Saalburg and his artwork. Also found are biographical material and subject files.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original material requires an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
Allen Saalburg (1899-1987) was a painter, illustrator, and innovative screenprinter who spent most of his career working in Frenchtown, New Jersey. From 1917 to 1920 he studied painting at the Pratt Institute and the Art Students League. In the late 1920s, Saalburg worked in Paris and had a solo exhibition at Galerie Bernheim-Jeune before returning to New York in 1930.
Throughout his career, Saalburg illustrated covers for popular magazines. His paintings were shown in group exhibitions at the Art Institute of Chicago and Whitney Museum of American Art. Solo exhibitions included shows at Grand Central Galleries and Kraushaar Galleries in New York, and others in New Jersey and Pennsylvania. He produced complex prints based on his paintings and experimented with screenprinting onto non-traditional surfaces. A piece on plastic panels was commissioned for a pavillion at the 1964 New York World's Fair.
Allen Saalburg's marriage to Muriel King, a costume and fashion designer, ended in divorce. His second wife was Mary Faulconer, a painter. Allen Saalburg died in 1987 in Flemington, New Jersey.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Executor Prudence Crowther donated the Allen Saalburg papers in 2004.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter, illustrator, and screenprinter Allen Saalburg, 1924-circa 2003, bulk 1940-1987, measure 0.8 linear feet. Included are professional correspondence, printed material, and a scrapbook. Most photographs are of Saalburg and his artwork. Also found are biographical material and subject files.
Biographical material consists of a chronology. Correspondence is with New York Graphic Society and Bucks County Historical Society, Doylestown, Pennsylvania. Business conducted by Canal Press and exhibitions at Ink River Gallery are documented in the subject files. Books and World War II posters illustrated by Saalburg are among the printed material. A scrapbook consists mainly of printed material illustrated by Saalburg. Photographs include views of his home in Uhlerstown, Pennsylvania and the studio, Canal Press, in Frenchtown, New Jersey. Also found are photographs of a trip to Albrook Air Force Base, Panama Canal Zone, where he participated in an exhibition featuring paintings of military planes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as 6 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, circa 2003 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1956-1969, 1982-1983 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Subject Files, circa 1950s-1994 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1940-circa 1980s (Boxes 1-2, OV 3; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1924-1927, 1941-1947 (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1930-circa 1980s (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Conditions Governing Access
The Allen Saalburg papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.
Photographs; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Artists' studios -- Photographs; Printers -- New York (State) -- New York; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Scrapbooks; World War, 1939-1945; Canal Press; Bucks County Historical Society; New York Graphic Society; Ink River Gallery
- Biographical Materials, circa 2003; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  The chronology, compiled by Joseph Ruszicka, a researcher hired by the donor, is a photocopy.
  - Allen Russell Saalburg Chronology, circa 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1982-1983; circa 1956-1969; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence concerns arrangements with New York Graphic Society to sell Saalburg prints and gifts of his artwork to the Bucks County Historial Society, Doylestown, Pennsylvania.
  - New York Graphic Society, circa 1956-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bucks County Historical Society, 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Subject Files, circa 1950s-1994; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  The file concerning Saalburg's studio, Canal Press, contains business records and printed material. Correspondence, printed material and sales records document Saalburg's exhibitions at Ink River Gallery.
  - Canal Press, Catalogs and Price Lists, circa 1950s - circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Canal Press, Expenses, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Canal Press, Sales, 1967-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ink River Gallery, circa 1980s-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Printed Material, 1940-circa 1980s; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  One folder of printed material is about Saalburg. The remaining folders contain books and other printed materials illustrated or designed by Saalburg. The posters were issued by the U.S. Office of War Information. Miscellaneous items are a periodical, and the program and invitation for a 1979 tribute to Claudius Charles Philipe.
  - Articles About Saalburg (1929-1939), circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Yankee Iron: The Story of the Eastern Malleable Iron Company, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Connecticut Enterprise, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Frenchtown, NJ, 1867-1967, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1940; 1979; Archival Resource Key; Oversized material housed in Box 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Posters, 1942-1943; Archival Resource Key; Oversized posters housed in OV 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Printed Materials from Box 1, Folder 12, 1940; 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Posters from Box 1, Folder 13, 1942-1943; Archival Resource Key; Some items are fragile (Box OV 3)
- Scrapbook, 1941 - 1947; 1924 - 1927; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  The scrapbook contains many periodical covers and articles illustrated by Saalburg. Also included are a few newspaper clippings mentioning him and "Allen Saalburg: Descriptive Artist," a 1947 article published in Arts.
  - Scrapbook, 1941-1947; 1924-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs, circa 1930-circa 1980s; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Photographs of Saalburg include studio portraits and informal snapshots. Some portraits are digitial copies of earlier images.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by subject. Additional photographs are found among the subject files (series 3).
  - Artwork by Saalburg - Glass Panels Printed by Silkscreen, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Color transparency
  - Artwork by Saalburg - Paintings, circa 1930-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Artwork by Saalburg - Laura Harding Collection of Screenpainted Furniture, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes negatives
  - People - Allen Saalburg, circa 1940s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - People - Allen Saalburg in Studio, 1958-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Places - Canal Press Studio, Frenchtown, New Jersey, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Places - Saalburg Home, Uhlerstown, Pennslyvania, circa 1970s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes 2 negatives and article about the building's history
  - Events - Air Force Trip with John Mooney, circa 1956-circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)